Grace Gallatin Seton-Thompson Papers, 1903-1940
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Grace Gallatin Seton-Thompson papers
1903-1940
Seton-Thompson, Grace Gallatin
MS 143
3 boxes (1.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Author; Travel writer; Feminist; Suffragist; and Relief worker, World War I. Includes printed material, correspondence, published writings and typescripts, memorabilia, notes, photographs, and organization files. Information relating to the International Council of Women, the National Council of Women, and the Montessori Education Association of New York.
Biographical Note
Grace Gallatin was born in Sacramento, California on January 28, 1872. In 1888 she began writing articles for San Francisco newspapers under the pen name of Dorothy Dodge, and in 1892 graduated from Packer Collegiate Institute, in Brooklyn, NY. She married Ernest Thompson Seton in 1896, a founder of the Boy Scouts of America. Their daughter Ann (known as 'Anya') was born in 1904. Active for women's rights, Grace Seton served as vice president and president of the Connecticut Woman's Suffrage Association (1910-20), was president of Pen and Brush (1898-1939), and with her husband, helped to organize the Girl Pioneers (later the Camp Fire Girls) in 1910. During World War I, she organized and directed a women's motor unit to aid soldiers in France. She was President of the National League of Pen Women from 1926 to 1928 and from 1930 to 1932. She helped organize an international conference of women writers at the Century of Progress Exposition in 1933 and arranged an exhibit of 3,000 books by women, which later became the core of the Biblioteca Femina at Northwestern University. In the 1920s and 1930s Seton visited Japan, China, Indochina, Hawaii, Egypt and Latin American and later wrote books about her travels, including A Woman Tenderfoot (1900) and A Woman Tenderfoot in Egypt (1923), Chinese Lanterns (1924), Yes, Lady Saheb (1925). Seton divorced in 1935. In the 1940s she followed Yogananda, traveling to his ashrams. She died in Palm Beach, Florida, March 19, 1959.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The collection includes biographical articles and clippings, correspondence, published writings and typescripts, memorabilia, notes, photographs, and organization files. Correspondence (1903-40) pertains to her travels, publications, and involvement in feminist and social organizations. Organizational files include minutes, agendas and reports relating to the International Council of Women (1915-26),the National Council of Women, and the Montessori Education Association of New York. Her work for the International Writers Conclave (Chicago, 1933) brought occasional correspondence from women authors around the world. Typescripts of articles and addresses including an essay on Chinese medicine and information on Dr. Mary Stone, medical missionary, China (n.d.). Material related to her world travels includes writings, correspondence, travel literature, maps and notes. Individuals represented include May Wright Sewall, Mary Eleanor Wilkins Freeman, Lena Madesin Phillips, and Kate Douglas Smith Wiggin.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
Grace Seton-Thompson donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1948 to 1950.
Search Terms
Boyle, Kay, 1902-; Freeman, Mary Eleanor Wilkins, 1852-1930; Phillips, Lena Madesin; Seton-Thompson, Grace Gallatin; Wiggin, Kate Douglas Smith, 1856-1923; International Council of Women--History--Sources; Montessori Educational Association; National Council of Women of the United States--History--Sources; National American Woman Suffrage Association--History--Sources; China--Description and travel--Sources; Indonesia--Description and travel--Sources; Feminists--United States--History--20th century; West (U.S.)--Description and travel--Sources; Women authors, American--20th century--Sources; Women hunters--History--20th century--Sources; Women travelers--History--20th century--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional papers are located at Boston University; Northwestern University (the Biblioteca Femina Collection); and the Schlesinger and Houghton Libraries at Harvard University. Most of Seton-Thompson's suffrage material went to Connecticut College.
- Biographical Materials
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1933-40 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Writings and speeches, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memorabilia, 1932-40, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Famous American Authors: Writer's Conclave, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  - International Council of Women: Book exhibit, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1931-33 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, 1933, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Suffrage
  - Biblioteca Femina, 1933-83 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Czecho-Slovak Benefit, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - International Council of Women: Writer's Conclave, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - International Council of Women, Paris, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Montessori Educational Association, 1915-16 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - National Council of Women, United States, 1931-35 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Suffrage: general, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Travel
  - Maps, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Travel brochures, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Travel reports and pamphlets, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Asia Magazine--Dutch East Indies Number, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Australia (Cromer, Spiritualist literature), 1928 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - British Isles, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - China: clippings and notes, 1929-31 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
  - England and Paris, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Far East: clippings, memorabilia and notes, 1930-31 (Box 3, Folder 7-9)
  - Hawaii, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Java, Sumatra, Singapore and Bali, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
- Books on Shelf
  - Woman Tenderfoot in Egypt, 1923